[SPEAKER_01]: So, if we continue by ānāpānasati, following from the previous discussion.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you breathe?
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you doing that?
[SPEAKER_03]: You inhale and then you exhale.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you inhale?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you exhale?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you lift your arms?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you stand up?
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you sit down?
[SPEAKER_01]: You intend to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is there anything in between the intention and the action of doing it?
[SPEAKER_01]: How does that... does that intention...
[SPEAKER_01]: Where does that intention go?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it enter the body and move your arm?
[SPEAKER_01]: Does it intend to breathe and breathe out?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is the intention?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is the body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where is the breath, in this case?
[SPEAKER_01]: You know the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: We'll be talking about it in some other video.
[SPEAKER_01]: Breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take a long breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take a short breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take a forceful breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take a light breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Where's the intention?
[SPEAKER_01]: Where's the breathing?
[SPEAKER_02]: I'd say the intention is underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is it, though?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly how you would start, but is it underneath?
[SPEAKER_01]: Underneath what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Underneath the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what is that intention when you look at it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's an image of the physical breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if there is no image of the physical breathing, there'll be no intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, why does it feel like underneath that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it does.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of the assumption of there being a relationship between the intention and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there is a relationship, so... You start with a relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's obviously wrongly assumed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But can people tell the details about that wrong assumption?
[SPEAKER_01]: Particulars?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this what, eh...
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, this is, I think, what I meant when we were talking last time, when I said there's like this kind of blurring of boundaries between the the intention to breathe that kind of makes the body do the breathing, and then you feel the body breathing, and you feel like you have... or the intention has caused the breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's obviously not something
[SPEAKER_03]: You're actively thinking, but it is implied in every bodily action.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's implied, for example, through regarding your intention as something under the breath, that already carries that overlap that cannot be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Overlap of the domains.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you start with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You start with what it actually... And even if somebody describes a difference, I might say, oh, I don't feel like it's on there.
[SPEAKER_01]: I feel like it's in here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, see, you realize any positionality, so to speak, in regard to the breath, assumes a relationship with it.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But...
[SPEAKER_01]: Assumes breath to come out of the intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, your intention, gratuitously, not knowing that it's actually impossible, takes up the body, presuming it's breathing, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, your thoughts take up your mouth when you speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when you think, and you say what you think, the implicit assumption is that it's those thoughts have become these words, have descended
[SPEAKER_01]: And turned into the sounds, there's this, as I said, kind of directionality from you outward, and same with the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, there... well, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the whole point of the practice, is to completely remove any traces of that directionality that implies ownership, and me here, doing these things through the body, through the speech, through the mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, how do you then breathe?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if the intention is not actually... cannot actually descend into the physical domain, cannot actually take it up, how do you breathe?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you not forget to breathe?
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can forget about breathing, but you never forget to breathe.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that you are doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is happening.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, who's doing it then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's not you who's doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're asking who's doing it, is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, who or what is doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unavoidably there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something is doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, intention is doing it, which is unavoidable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How?
[SPEAKER_01]: How can intention be there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, sorry, the body, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's no...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the body is doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In its bodily domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: On account of your intention, in its intentional domain,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's even that that goes...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm thinking, if I say the body is doing it...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you just say the body is doing it, then, obviously, it can be misunderstood.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you say it at the end of all this questioning, then it's hopefully clear what we mean by that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, presence of intention makes the body breathe.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's no relationship between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those two domains don't connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no live wire that connects the intentional domain and touches the body and then snaps it into breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just intention to breathe is here and body breathing is here.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's nothing in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no directionality, overlap, connection in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just
[SPEAKER_01]: Your intention to breathe exists in its own domain, directed in its own direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneous to that, there is the body corresponding to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the relationship...
[SPEAKER_01]: If there were to be a relationship, it's inconceivable by you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were let out from that relationship.
[SPEAKER_01]: But see, even thinking that there is an external relationship between them, that I'm not privy to,
[SPEAKER_01]: can become your assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's really the only way to reach the point of not assuming the impossible relationship between the two internally, is to undo any notion, tacit assumptions of overlap, of directionality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, what's left?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, is the conscious body in name and form, externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: The domain of the breathing body and everything else, external name and form.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's really the training of ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's undermined at very first, very subtle, very easily done, because it's already a starting point, connection between
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole point of the intentional, those steps in ānāpānasati, where you're intentionally breathing like this or like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not shying away from intentional involvement with the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once, obviously, the proper mind recollectedness and knowledge of the breath is established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you want to hammer it in.
[SPEAKER_01]: That no matter how forceful, how determined, how intentional your intention is, it remains fully enclosed within its own domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the body doesn't even know about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But look, it's happening because of the intention.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, that still doesn't mean they connect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in any measurable way by you internally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you stretch the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, once you start undoing or seeing through the gratuitous assumption of this directionality, from my intention the breath comes, you realize the breathing is always underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body, the domain of the body is always underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: Underneath your domain of intentions, underneath the domain of your feelings, underneath the domain of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly why you start stretching the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Breathing in like this, I'll experience the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: Breathing in like this, breathing out like this, I'll experience the feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll experience the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll experience the dhammas, the images.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the body is inaccessible, underneath, and the correspondence of bodily actions and presence of mental reactions has no measurable directionality, overlap, connection, not even a trace,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, there's absolutely... in the very core, there is nothing that you can deem, yeah, but this came from me.
[SPEAKER_01]: This has originated from me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it completely undermines the perception of any mastery.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize, even when I intend, I only know it worked because the body over there
[SPEAKER_01]: You breathe into it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Happened to do it, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Happened to do it to an account of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: And even that, you only kind of know indirectly, like, as in, you have to... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even that, it's underneath.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's kind of underneath that.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly why, well, at some point, you will stop breathing, despite how strong you will intend to breathe.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not be able to.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was gonna say, actually, because those...
[SPEAKER_03]: This is something I was thinking about, like,
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know how to put this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so, let's say with speaking, like, it's very, it's quite clear that at the moment when I speak, when I actually speak, I can only do it by kind of looking past the actual thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I was starting to notice that there is... it feels like there's a corresponding thing with the intention to breathe.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if I actually become... if I'm very aware... Well, that's what you're training against.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your training is supposed to undo that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That... because, yes, of course, every intentional involvement will make you look past the intentional to the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why it just naturally leads to that assumption of the physicality, the connection with it, that whole...
[SPEAKER_01]: Proliferation that takes place on account of simply not knowing that those things are not connectable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like developing the perception of that... well, developing the practice, say, of the intentional breathing, whereby intention does not spill out into the juxtaposed physical domain that exists in its own extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then,
[SPEAKER_01]: The perceptions of that physical domain that exists in, in some extent, you use to undermine any other intentional involvement, not necessarily in regard to breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In regard to any feeling that's present, in regard to any mind state, in regard to any pressure, there is the body breathing underneath it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And just to the extent that you know that correctly, to that extent, the domain that's pressuring you to take up the directionality,
[SPEAKER_01]: To follow it, it's kind of frozen, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: You freeze it in its own extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if the pressure remains within it, you are not the one pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, practicing in regard to these four things, there'll be nothing... well, there'll be no more... there'll be no place left for any assumed overlaps and connections to exist.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be like that simile in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: A skilled monk is like a butcher that cuts up a cow and completely, clearly, fully separates, piles its meat, tendon, bones, organs, clearly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you realize, oh, yeah, they were piled up together, but they were never one with each other or blending one into another.
[SPEAKER_01]: Always clearly separate things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, people often misunderstand that as some sort of dry intellectual analysis of elements.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you approach it phenomenologically, you realize, no, those domains are phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're aggregates of phenomena, and you see them in its own extent, in its full extent, completely independent of each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's the five heaps.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not one heap.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter how much it's heaped up, you will always discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: rūpa, vedanā, sañña, sankhāra, viññāṇa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And anything in this layer that belongs to sañña, goes to sañña.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's understood under a sañña domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything belongs under vedanā, it's understood under vedanā domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter the specifics.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're intentionally breathing differently, long, short, knowingly, but not for the sake of breathing, but for the sake of fully, kind of, dragging out an implicit assumption that at least some degree of your intentionality flows into the physical and makes you breathe.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the result of that is a perception of complete, utter confinement.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not as unpleasant as if it were to be discovered through the contemplation of death or a subha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that body, that domain of body breathing there, always has been like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Independent of you, having a life of its own, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither good nor bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, ah, it's fairly neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although you're completely confined within it, you realize you're confined within the neutrality, and that's not a problem, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, as I was saying, in our Thojan group, the... if you feel undermined by that domain that's inaccessible, that's now being unblurred,
[SPEAKER_01]: This juxtaposition has been clearly outlined.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no means of accessing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you feel anxiety or something on account of being undermined, you realize, well, that's undermined.
[SPEAKER_01]: The anxious chip is equally undermined by this thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but what if then doubt starts arising?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's undermined by the enduring breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That reveals the domain of juxtaposed physicality.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's basically like the complete unmanagement of, like, just undermining whether you want it or not, regardless of whatever can possibly come up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Including, like, the feelings on account of that very practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was asking when we were in Samādhipa recently, talking about this with the monks there, what was that sutta?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I was saying, I remember there is a sutta where the Buddha compared
[SPEAKER_01]: And, I think, where were we?
[SPEAKER_01]: I said, I think, Majjima 28 or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember, but we did mention it a few talks back.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was those cryptic... Well, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: This was different.
[SPEAKER_01]: This was like the cryptic lines about the anthill.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was going to say, I think it might be that one of those, like a bar.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he pulls a bar, and he pulls this out of this thing that he's digging up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, basically, that's the avijja, the bar.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's sort of... one end lays on your intentional domain, another end lays on your physical domain, because you don't know that it can't.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, removing the connection between those domains, those fields, keeps the... fields remain intact, as they always were, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: By that entire internal directionality that implies ownership, that implies eternal is mine, all of that, that's just gone.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why I'm just thinking, that's why it's like it's quite important to actually to start with how it genuinely feels or like the the the sense of the connection that is there rather than
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's the only way you can start, if you're honest.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can't...
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start approaching it with your wrong views, then, yeah, it's going to be like some system of thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, there are no things... there's no connection, and now I must, like, see that there is no connection.
[SPEAKER_03]: In reality, there is no connection.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I have to kind of... and all of that is going to leave out.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, in reality, there is connection.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is your reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to undermine it, not through your...
[SPEAKER_01]: Abstract thought and developing systems and the ideas of structure or external things because of which this all is.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You undermine it through the practice we just described.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, obviously, presumably, person is withdrawn from the centrality, correct sense of strength.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already a form of undermining.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, on top of that, any... any perceptions that you have of your own physicality are undermined by the domain of body breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any intentions, any state of citta, whether it's elated, depressed, afraid, happy, all that's second to the juxtaposed domain of... inaccessible domain of the body breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any images, any thoughts, you realize, oh, they are simultaneous, but they exist in its own domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the point is... well, another point worth mentioning is you don't have to be trying now to catch or police all these little intentions like scratch my face or, I don't know, adjust the seating position or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that... yes, that too carries the implication.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not... that's not the reason for the implication of the connection of the domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the intentions rooted in greed, aversion, delusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: are the sources of the ignorance, of the bridge.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you undo those, then all these other ones will sort themselves out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I was thinking that as well, like, there's no... it's like, in the same way, there's no problem with breathing, in the sense, it's not a... it's a completely neutral action, but just by virtue of all of these other
[SPEAKER_03]: Actions being done around every possible action carries the same implication.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you use a neutral action that you can... that observe, quote-unquote, while in... with a calm mind, that is not occupied by hindrances, in order to, like, uproot or kind of see that assumption in real life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And somebody who is doing that, they might even feel like
[SPEAKER_01]: Too much of a craving, or a kind of sense of duty, to see it correctly.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, even then, you continue breathing and you undermine that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't stop it, because it feels unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It feels unpleasant, not because of the breathing, but because of your expectation in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I must see it like this, I must see it like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, citta is getting upset, getting affected, getting pressured.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like proper breathing is down there, in its own domain, inaccessible, underneath all of this mess.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not about stopping the mess, getting rid of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about undermining it with, well, correctly discerned basis, what's underneath.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, with correctly developed yoniso manasikāra, you would undermine it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's the yoniso of whatever you're attending that recognizes the physicality of the body breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how it goes away.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind comes down.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thoughts, on account of being pressured by that mind, come down as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like how the simile in the sutra says.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the rain comes, then just the dust that was in the air just settles.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's the comparison for ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's through indirect means you settle the dust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not through catching the particles of dust one by one, as they fly around.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's reminded me of another thing, that, like, last time you were asking,
[SPEAKER_03]: Just even in broad terms, like, how do you start doing ānāpānasati?
[SPEAKER_03]: And what I was thinking was that probably the most, what I would say, like, the most accurate way would be basically, like, the point is, you need to be restraining your bodily intentions, restraining your verbal intentions, dwelling in seclusion, restraining your mental intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: And while you're doing all of that, it's not really
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not that useful to try to do ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more like once you're doing all of that and now you kind of recognize you're able... there's a thought pressuring you and you're able to not give it attention.
[SPEAKER_03]: What you find yourself with is basically the things you can be mindful of.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason for that is because if you do it before, your intentions would not have been
[SPEAKER_01]: Softened, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're still way too charged with craving, with this, with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, when you turn that to breathing, you're just going to be doing it again through the same perversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you would have been withdrawn from our state's restraint, that's already, as I said, removing that that stiffness of that direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, yes, you might still have traces of it, and you start doing the breathing, and you're still doing them with the, as I said, intentions of expectations and craving involved, but there is enough space through that looseness of these intentions to now see them, see the underlying body, unconnected with it, just exist over there.
[SPEAKER_01]: My intention goes up, up here, and as I said, the result of it, seeming result of it, is simultaneous body breathing down there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, of course,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you cultivate more, make macho, as they say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Encourage monks to keep doing it, because it will just be peeling off layer by layer by layer of that connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is an assumption, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's exactly like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think we mentioned last time.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if it was recorded or afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, the ānāpānasati,
[SPEAKER_01]: brings the satipaṭṭhānas to fulfillment, which brings the four right strivings, which brings seven enlightenment factors, which is just a different way of saying it purifies you completely and you're an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: An ānāpānasati was taught to at least sotāpannas in an ānāpānasati sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will quite clearly describe that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then there are suttas where it's said that satipaṭṭhāna can be taught as a means of those who don't have the right view
[SPEAKER_01]: Develop it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not any Tom, Dick and Harry without a right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like the monks that would have already been living in restraint with patimokkha, withdrawn from unwholesome states, guarding their sense doors, moderate in eating, dwelling in seclusion, but still don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what you said.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if you haven't met these aspects of the gradual training,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, doing satipaṭṭhāna will be done with your craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the only sutta that mentions... Every other instance of satipaṭṭhāna or ānāpānasati is basically taught to the monks that already had the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this sutta does specifically say that you could teach it even to those monks that don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, okay, they don't have the right view, but they would have lived pretty trained already in
[SPEAKER_01]: Softening those rigid, assumed directions of their ownership, intentionality, craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like, okay, so they already have a degree of yoniso.
[SPEAKER_01]: Degree of yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: So now, get them to do this contrasting practice to undermine it further and to then just see it how it should be seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people often take that sutta to say, see, you don't have to be a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then latch on to that technicality, ignoring the major technicality that they're not fulfilling, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: they're not a monk, they're not celibate, they're not withdrawn from sensuality, they don't dwell in seclusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you want to be technical, those are the absolute necessities.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you could see, as I said, because it's... that's already the beginning of satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you don't specifically are doing
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarification and discernment of these four domains, body, feeling, mind and thoughts, by not following sensuality at its face value, by not following, by being celibate, by being withdrawn from distractions, quite important, by dwelling secluded, physically secluded, you are already highlighting these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you'll be, you will be able to recognize it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you haven't built up these things, well, there's nothing for you to recognize, because it's not there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that was all, like, in relation to satipaṭṭhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think when it comes to ānāpānasati, that's even a bit more specific.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I don't think you'll be able to do it without a right view at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you were perfectly... Well, maybe, theoretically, I suppose, there might be a monk that's quite established in yoniso, withdrawn, but just... just so close, but not seeing it, and then working, grinding through the ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the pain of undermining his sense of self through that might be enough, but he might be able to unbear his own craving for the expectations of the result.
[SPEAKER_03]: It might be worth mentioning, when you sit down to do ānāpānasati, do you need to close your eyes?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no such thing as meditation with closed eyes, even in the broadest sense of meditation that we would have used.
[SPEAKER_01]: Certainly, no meditation in terms of a technique that you do, but somebody could take the description, yes, you sit down and you play in the wood, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: you breathe like this, you breathe like this, so to undermine your own intentionality in regard to breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can take that as something they do, because it is a form of doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that whole idea of why it's closed, I think that probably came from some yogic practices that tried to wrap their head around the Buddhist jhāna, but couldn't quite understand it, so mystified it themselves.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just that you go into a fantasy world.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: You self-hypnotize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You read any self-hypnosis instruction, and it's all exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And actually, there was, I remember, in Sri Lanka there was this
[SPEAKER_01]: The common meditation instruction is like you look about three or four feet in front of you for a brief... well, for a period of time and then you kind of sort of start squinting and you let your eye... and then you close your eyes and get into your casino, meditation object or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I found this self-hypno... hypnosis techniques.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was doing exactly the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's look like
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, a meter ahead of you, and then start intending your eyelids being heavy, feeling them as really heavy, until your eyes naturally close, and then start distributing these energies of your breath through the different parts of your body, and feeling it, and like, and it was just, like, again, not, not that they were, they obviously thought it's a good self-hypnosis, it's a good idea, and then you enter this hypnotic state, and it was actually in a book about hypnosis,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and they thought it was a great thing to deal with suffering, to numb yourself to it, to distract yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, the whole idea of meditating with your eyes closed, rightly or wrongly, whatever your meditation is, it's... well, that's wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Destruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, there is absolutely no way that you will remain the clarity of perception in regard to the different domains that we talk about, if you start closing your eyes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you can do that almost, just almost, as a kind of a natural assumption, even if you, you know, try and do all of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: That already, practically speaking, that already divorces you from any, any correct basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It kind of assumes that the problem is in the object, like in what I perceive, like I will be destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it certainly, it enables imagination a lot more.
[SPEAKER_01]: When your eyes are closed, the mind, the thoughts just pick up, the energies just flow, and then you start... you start basically dreaming, yeah, while you're awake.
[SPEAKER_01]: And... no, no, no, it's absolutely not a question of eyes closed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, yeah, you can... it's a... it's a way to imagine a fantasy world.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can imagine a fantasy world much better and much easier with your eyes closed and your brains open.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, keeping your eyes open just keeps things so mundane.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's quite boring and depressing, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I love the kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Doubt.
[SPEAKER_03]: Am I doing it right?
[SPEAKER_03]: And the eyes are open.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're forced to kind of be awake to that whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you close your eyes, it's like just... You can imagine things like a breath coming into your neck, coming, running down your throat.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you're building up this fantasy world of these breath energies.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's now become your views.
[SPEAKER_01]: We call it fantasy and hypnosis and trance and dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you actually don't, if you think it's a valid thing, all those...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, the hypnosis and self-induced trances are real things as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that it's not real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, if you don't see it for what it is, experiencing those things will just be now fueling your views.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're going to develop these views of these objective existing energies and kundalinis and stuff over there that you just need to tap into.
[SPEAKER_01]: All driven by your... by your, like as I said, hypnotic-induced fantasy that made your body feel like it's not there and light and energy and the perception of light.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's always the perception of light.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your head fills with light.
[SPEAKER_01]: I read that through these kundalini accounts, some contemporary jhāna teachers, it's just this... it's all like... like the light... the light and the... like you... the... the rushing sounds in your ears and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like... how is that different than any sound that you hear?
[SPEAKER_01]: How is it different than any light that you perceive?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it so special?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it's special because it just feels supernatural.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just feels different.
[SPEAKER_01]: indifferent is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, the measure, then, of your success and your accomplishment is just novelty, as I said, induced.
[SPEAKER_01]: But novelty runs out.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to keep doing more and more, because it will become mundane.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I think, for more people, it's the view that's implicit, that they would have freed themselves from suffering for a period of time, when they were unaware of their suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they're unaware of the inherent undermining of their human existence, that's constantly undermined by the independence of the aggregates, that there is absolutely no place for safety, four mountains coming, crushing everything, there is no, like, not even a millimeter you can hide.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you develop the idea of the ecstatic trance that's outside of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's my safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, this is actually outside of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know the Buddha said there is nothing outside of the aggregates, but this consciousness is outside of the aggregates, because it's just so special.
[SPEAKER_01]: Please don't take it away from me.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you do have
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the validity of the reality of this belief that I have now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that was factually experienced.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's like those evangelical preachers, when they sort of rally people up in big groups, and they start feeling this roar of the whole stadium, and they say, you see that what you feel?
[SPEAKER_01]: I was like, yeah, I mean, we all factually feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's Jesus.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, okay, must be.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because I have factually felt that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now he provided a little input as to what that really was.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now I hold the belief that I did experience the divine.
[SPEAKER_01]: In reality, you go to any football match, you're gonna experience the same thing, at least in Eastern Europe.
[SPEAKER_01]: When a thousand people are screaming the same thing, it just feels like a massive war cry.
[SPEAKER_01]: And even if you're completely disinterested, you're gonna feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The roar, the sound, the vibration, the mass.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, if you take the approach from the suttas, you realize it doesn't matter the novelty, doesn't matter how new, how big, how great, how lofty,
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience of feeling is the experience of feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception?
[SPEAKER_01]: Perception is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness?
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing special.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you completely experience dispassion towards aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing special in any form of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the most divine two-sitter heavens, it's still the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the worst of the hells, it's still the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: Equal dispassion?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's why you won't appear in any of those places.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like that unawareness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can even just say, okay, well, I don't even want novelty experiences or anything, but I... And it's not wrong to say that meditation, even correct meditation, is a kind of a form of relaxing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but there's a big fat line between just relaxing and entering a trance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's exactly what I'm... my point, basically, is that, like, relaxing always is basically associated with unawareness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not... Because people don't know when to stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: They start through relaxing and then they start very much doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they become, as I said, hypnotized.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you relax, as we discussed in the previous video, only to the extent that it was active.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start relaxing more than that, that becomes your new activity.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're not peaceful, you're not calm, and you certainly won't be relaxed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Although you might feel very pleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you completely be unaware and kind of... that's the closest you can get to feeling actually relaxed.